

About

Birthdate: 28.05.1988 Nationality: Swiss

Contact

- **♀** Fichtenstrasse 32, 9230 Flawil, CH
- D +41 79 954 84 50
- ✓ aurelien.sallin@protonmail.com
- ngithub.com/asallin
- http://asallin.github.io

Languages

French (mother tongue)
English (full proficiency)
Italian (full proficiency)
German (full proficiency)
Swiss German (good understanding)

Programming Skills

R Software

MS Office

ETEX

</> Python

</>
> Stata

P Git

SQL

Power BI

Aurélien Sallin, PhD

Economist | Data Scientist

I am a driven economist, data scientist, and teacher with a background in Philosophy and over 6 years of academic and corporate experience in the field of data science, economic research, consulting, health insurance, and university teaching.

I thrive most in creative and collaborative analytical roles that answer *WHY* questions. I value above all energizing collaborations with dedicated colleagues, and a space to devise unforeseen solutions that positively influence organizations, decision-makers, and the greater good.

Professional experience

2022-PRESENT

Expert in Health Care Research & Member of Management

SWICA Health Insurance – Third leading health and accident insurer in Switzerland with 1.5 million insured persons and 28,000 corporate clients.

- Successfully worked on 15+ business cases, including causal evaluation of E-health innovative telemedicine tools, causal evaluation of adherence to clinical guidelines in routine data, analysis of costs trends
- Offered strategic and data-driven recommendations in the field of integrated care, alternative financing models, smart medicine, and health economics
- Put together a team of 5+ researchers and experts to push the use of ML methods for time-series analysis of prescription behaviors
- Presentation of research and analytics projects in national and international pharma and health care conferences (Interpharma Basel (2022), SAMW Bern (2023), "Junge Wissenschaft und Praxis" Berlin 2023)
- Active in the health innovation start up scene as a member of the "USZ Health Innovation Hub Expert Panel" from the University Hospital Zürich

2017-JAN.2024

(Senior) Researcher & Lecturer

Swiss Institute for Empirical Economic Research, University of St. Gallen (HSG)

- Successful management and completion of 5+ research projects in education and health economics
- Teaching data science to 200+ BA students as the lead instructor
- Focus on quantitative methods for research in causal inference using "Big Data", text data and NLP, geocoded data, and network data.
- Developed expertise in using standard econometric methods, machine learning, and optimal treatment allocation algorithms
- Presentations in 20+ leading international economic conferences and publication of one chapter of my dissertation in a top-field international scientific journal

Earlier professional experiences

Research Assistant and Data Analyst, Chairs of Public Finance and of Development Economics, University of Fribourg (2015-2016) — **Research Assistant**, Chair of Ethics and Political Philosophy, University of Fribourg (2014-2015) — **Pontifical Swiss Guard**, Vatican City (2009-2011).

Hobbies

Sports

Running and biking

Music

Piano (Diploma, Conservatoire de Fribourg, 2008) Classical Singing (Certificate, Conservatoire de Fribourg, 2015) Many choral experiences.

Cooking

Sourdough bread, vegetarian cooking, fermentation

Selected Portfolio

Programming in Causal ML

itscausal: An R package for applications in the area of "Interrupted Time Series" using machine learning methods in the context of health insurance claim data •

"Brand Awareness" and Scientific Contributions

Small data analyses for SWICA's "Number of the Month"

Estimation of potential CO2 emissions savings through the reduction of avoidable hospitalizations using Monte-Carlo simulations

Causal ML

Causal Machine Learning and Optimal Policy for the evaluation of special education programs ☒

Causal ML for network data in the field of education economics ❖

E-Health & Technologies

Evaluation of the use of "TytoCare" (an innovative telemedicine device) on the behavior of SWICA customers using a "Differences-in-Differences" study (internal, *)

Ethics and Philosophy

Understanding and Dealing with Climate Grief: An LBT Approach, International Journal of Philosophical Practice, 2021

→)

Education

2022

PhD in Economics and Finance

University of St. Gallen HSG With highest distinction ("Summa cum Laude", 5.84/6)

- Title: "Minorities in Schools: Three Empirical Essays in Education Economics"
- Award for the best dissertation in Econometrics in the PhD in Economics and Finance program
- Visiting scholar at Lund University, Sweden (2021), and at the Federal Reserve of Chicago, USA (2022)

2018

Master of Arts in Philosophy

University of Fribourg

"Summa cum Laude" (5.81/6)

• MA thesis: "Decision-Making under Moral Uncertainty". Supervisor: G. Soldati

2017

Master of Arts in Economics

University of Fribourg

"Summa cum Laude" (5.76/6)

- MA thesis: "Does Culture Matter in Mortgage Preferences? Evidence from the Real-Estate Market in Switzerland". Supervisors: M. Schelker and M. Brown (HSG)
- Exchange semester at the HSG St. Gallen

2014

Bachelor of Arts in Philosophy, Minor in Economics

University of Fribourg — "Insigni Cum Laude" (5.73/6) in Philosophy, "Summa cum Laude" (5.52/6) in Economics

Certifications

2023 **Design Thinking (basics)**

ITMP, St. Gallen, CH

2023 **Projekt Management: Grundlagen**

SWICA, St. Gallen, CH

2020 Logic-Based-Therapy practitioner

National Philosophical Counseling Association (NPCA), Florida, USA

Volunteering/Other

2015-PRESENT

Board Member, Advisor & Coach

InterGifted – Leading international support organization for intellectually gifted adults offering assessments, coaching, professional & personal development.

- Business development from inception and long-range planning
- Coordination and leadership of a community with 1000+ members
- Coached 10+ adult gifted clients on their careers using Logic-based therapy

2023-PRESENT

Active member & Committe member

Green liberal party (glp), glp Wil Land, St. Gallen